<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<xml>
<include src="settings/generic.xml"/>
<synopsis name="I Agree!"
	description="agreed."
		keywords="agree"
/>
<title>Download RoboFab</title>
<div class="content">
	
	
	<h1>RoboFab License Agreement</h1>


	<p>
		Copyright (c) 2005-2007 The RoboFab Developers
	</p>
	<p>
	Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
	of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
	in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
	to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
	copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
	furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:
	</p>

	<p>
	The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
	all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
	</p>

	<p>
	THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
	IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
	FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
	AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
	LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
	OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
	THE SOFTWARE.
	</p>
	
	
<h1>Download RoboFab 1.1.1 Public Release</h1>

<p>
So you have <a href="download/license.html">read</a> and agreed to the <a href="http://robofab.org/download/license.html">License Agreement</a>. Select the RoboFab installer in the archive format of choice.
All installers contain the same code and support files. They're just packaged differently.
</p>

<h2>RoboFab + FontTools + Stuff for FontLab 5.0x on OSX</h2>
<p>
	Special one-click installer for RoboFab, FontTools and Numeric. This will install all dependencies compiled for PPC, and Python2.3.5 the way FontLab 5.0x likes i.

<br/>
	<a href="download/RoboFab1.1.1_FontLab_Installer.zip">RoboFab Installer for OSX, FontLab 5.0x</a>
	</p>

<h2>RoboFab + FontTools Combo Deluxe</h2>
<p>If you don't have fontTools or don't know what fontTools is, take this version. It will install RoboFab and the appropriate FontTools at the same time. FontTools still has a dependency on an older version of Numeric.
</p>


<h3>Stuffit archive</h3>
<p>
<a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1_PlusFontTools.dmg">RoboFab 1.1.1  Plus FontTools (dmg)</a>
</p>

<h3>Zip</h3>
<p>
<a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1_PlusFontTools.zip">RoboFab 1.1.1 Plus FontTools (zip)</a>
</p>


<h2>RoboFab Happy Meal</h2>
<p>In case you have a seperate fontTools install you want to use, these installers contain only RoboFab.




</p>


<h3>Stuffit archive</h3>
<p>
<a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1.dmg">RoboFab 1.1.1 (dmg)</a>
</p>

<h3>Zip</h3>
<p>
<a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1.zip">RoboFab 1.1.1 (zip)</a>
</p>



<h3>Numeric</h3>
<p>
	FontTools depends for certain operations on an older version of Numeric. This is the right package. If you want to install this on OSX (and you don't want to use the nice installer listed above) you need to install the OSX Developer Tools first. These can be found on the OSX installer DVD.
	<br/>
	<a href="download/Numeric-24.2.zip">Numeric 24.2</a>
</p>	





<h2>Old releases</h2>
<p>
Old releases <a href="download/old/">are here.</a>
</p>




</div>
</xml>
