<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?><xml><include src="settings/generic.xml"/><synopsis name="Download RoboFab"	description="download options and installers."		keywords="download installer"/><title>Download RoboFab</title><div class="content">			<h1>RoboFab License Agreement (BSD License)</h1><p>	Copyright (c) 2003-2007, The RoboFab Developers, Just van Rossum, Tal Leming, Erik van Blokland</p><p>	All rights reserved.</p><p>	Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:<ul>	<li>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</li>	<li>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</li>	<li>Neither the name of the RoboFab Developers nor the names of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific prior written permission.</li></ul></p><p>	THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS	"AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT	LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR	A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR	CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL,	EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,	PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR	PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF	LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING	NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS	SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</p>		<p><a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.php">This is the BSD license</a></p>	<h1>Download RoboFab 1.1.1 Public Release</h1><p>Select the RoboFab installer in the archive format of choice.All installers contain the same code and support files. They're just packaged differently.</p><h2>RoboFab + FontTools + Stuff for FontLab 5.0x on OSX</h2><p>	Special one-click installer for RoboFab, FontTools and Numeric. This will install all dependencies compiled for PPC, and Python2.3.5 the way FontLab 5.0x likes it.<br/>	<a href="download/RoboFab1.1.1_FontLab_Installer.zip">RoboFab Installer for OSX, FontLab 5.0x</a><br/>FontTools has the BSD license. <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/fonttools/">Check the FontTools project page for more info.</a>	</p>			<h2>RoboFab + FontTools Combo Deluxe</h2><p>If you don't have fontTools or don't know what fontTools is, take this version. It will install RoboFab and the appropriate FontTools at the same time. FontTools still has a dependency on an older version of Numeric.</p><h3>Stuffit archive</h3><p><a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1_PlusFontTools.dmg">RoboFab 1.1.1  Plus FontTools (dmg)</a></p><h3>Zip</h3><p><a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1_PlusFontTools.zip">RoboFab 1.1.1 Plus FontTools (zip)</a></p><h2>RoboFab Happy Meal</h2><p>In case you have a seperate fontTools install you want to use, these installers contain only RoboFab.</p><h3>Stuffit archive</h3><p><a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1.dmg">RoboFab 1.1.1 (dmg)</a></p><h3>Zip</h3><p><a href="download/current/RoboFab_1.1.1.zip">RoboFab 1.1.1 (zip)</a></p><h3>Numeric</h3><p>	FontTools depends for certain operations on an older version of Numeric. This is the right package. If you want to install this on OSX (and you don't want to use the nice installer listed above) you need to install the OSX Developer Tools first. These can be found on the OSX installer DVD.	<br/>	<a href="download/Numeric-24.2.zip">Numeric 24.2</a>		<br/><a href="http://numpy.scipy.org/">The Numeric Python Homepage</a> if you want to find out more about <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/numpy/">current versions</a> and licensing of Numeric.</p>	</div></xml>