<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<xml>
	<include src="settings/generic.xml" />
	<synopsis generate="1" name="How to make a UFO" description="export and import UFO's in FontLab" keywords="howto export ufo font" />
	<title>How to make a UFO</title> 

	<div class="content">
		<h1>How to make a UFO</h1> 
		<p>
		Exporting a FontLab font to UFO is easy.
		</p>
		<ul>
		<li>open the .vfb</li>
		<li>select the <strong>RoboFabUFO</strong> menu in the Macro toolbar</li>
		<li>select the <strong>Export Current Font to UFO Format</strong> script</li>
		<li>run it</li>
		
		</ul>
		<p>
		The .ufo will be in the same directory as the original .vfb file. Have an in-depth look at the <a href="ufo/index.html">ufo format here</a>.
		</p>
		
		<p class="note">
		If you want to export a new FontLab font to UFO, <strong>it is important that you save the font to .vfb first.</strong>
		</p>
		
		<h2>Importing a UFO into FontLab</h2>

		<ul>
		<li>select the <strong>RoboFabUFO</strong> menu in the Macro toolbar</li>
		<li>select the <strong>Import .ufo File into FontLab</strong> script</li>
		<li>run it</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>
		This script create a new, empty FontLab font, then proceed to ask you for a .ufo directory. 

		</p>
		
		<p class="note">
		Due to some limitations in how FontLab keeps track of new, untitled, unsaved fonts, it is vital to <strong>make sure that there are no other unsaved, untitled fonts open</strong> when you run this script. Because if there are, FontLab will be confused about where to import the glyphs from the .ufo and none of the fonts will show the new glyphs. It's ok to have other fonts open when importing .ufo, they just to have been saved previously.
		</p>
		
		<h3>Importing a bunch of UFO's into FontLab</h3>
		<p>
		What if you need to import a whole family of UFO's?
		</p>

		<ul>
		<li>select the <strong>RoboFabUFO</strong> menu in the Macro toolbar</li>
		<li>select the <strong>Import all UFO's in a folder</strong> script</li>
		<li>run it</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>
		This script will prompt you for a folder with UFO's. Pick one. The script will proceed to import the UFO's one by one.
		</p>
		
		<p class="note">
		Sometimes, some versions of FontLab can get a bit tired of importing UFO's in a batch. When this happens not all UFO's will be imported and FontLab may crash. When this happens, just import the fonts one by one.
		</p>
		
		
		<h3>Making a UFO from a font binary</h3>
		<p>
		Using FontTools you can make a UFO directly from a font binary. This is very fast, and it works outside of FontLab, but not all data (for instance kerning and apperently metrics) is imported. So your mileage may vary.
		</p>
		
		<pythonsource src="examples/makeufoBinary.py"/>

<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
</div>
</xml>
